A Guide to the Francis B. Harrison Papers 1735-1938
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Francis B. Harrison Papers 1735-1938
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
#1289, #1293, #1308, #1325, #1417
This collection consists of 111 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These accessions were made a gift to the Library by the Honorable Francis Burton Harrison of Charlottesville, Virginia: #1289 and #1289-a on November 29 and December 6, 1941; #1308 on December 27, 1941; #1325 on January 13, 1942. #1293 was loaned to the Library by the Honorable Francis B. Harrison on December 8, 1941. #1417 was purchased by the Library on May 2, 1942.
Scope and Content Information
This collection is comprised of 111 items, 1735-1938, mostly papers from the families of both of Francis B. Harrison's parents--the Harrisons of New Orleans and the Carys of Virginia. Francis B. Harrison (1873- 1957) and his two brothers, Fairfax and Archibald, were born and reared in New York City, where their father Burton Harrison (1839?-1904), earlier President Jefferson Davis' private secretary, was an attorney.
Their mother, Constance Cary Harrison (1843-1920), was the author of many articles and novels chronicling the life of the first families of Virginia. Through generations of marriage, the Carys were related to virtually all of the well-known Virginia clans: the Jeffersons, Carrs, Randolphs, Tuckers, Carters and the Lords Fairfax, and so her stories and articles carried a great air of authenticity. Her memoir, Recollections Grave and Gay (1911), fills in an important segment in the social history of the Southern noncombatant population during the Civil War
Francis Harrison followed his brother Fairfax and his father in graduating from Yale, but thereafter pursued a career in politics. He served as congressman from New York in 1903-05, and from 1907 to 1913, and Governor-General of the Philippine Islands from 1913 to 1921.
Most of the items in the collection are inherited from his mother. They include originals and copies of his Grandfather Archibald Cary's letters, magazine articles written by his mother, copies of 18th century letters to family members, and miscellaneous letters of his mother's. From his father's family are included original newspaper editorials written by Jesse Burton Harrison, Francis B. Harrison's grandfather and the editor of the Louisiana Advertiser in 1836, and miscellaneous letters to J. B. Harrison written in the 1830s.
There are many items of interest to the social and political historian in this collection. Of special note are Archibald Cary's letters to his sister Patsy Jefferson Cary detailing trips to cities on the eastern seaboard (1837-1838), and his letters to his older brother Wilson Miles Cary. These letters comment faithfully on life in the deep South between 1837 and 1843, dwelling on both social and political themes.
The editorials written by J. B. Harrison on the eve of the 1836 presidential election illustrate the Whig point of view, and grassroots political action and organization. Although difficult to decipher, the diary kept by J. B. Harrison in 1829 and 1830 when he was studying in Germany gives valuable insights into European life and the later stages of the Romantic movement. The letter, ca. 1735, from Colonel William Byrd to Sir John Randolph provides an amusing exchange between two very prominent colonial Virginians. Likewise, the letter, 1763, from Colonel Wilson Cary to his daughter Elizabeth, Lady Fairfax, provides a homely glimpse of the apex of colonial Virginia society.
Contents List
- Colonel William Byrd to Sir John Randolph (copy) 1735 Jan 21
  [An amusing plea for foreign or domestick [sic] news from Williamsburg #1289
- Colonel Wilson Cary to Mrs. Brian Fairfax (copy) 1763 May
  nee Elizabeth Cary. A father to daughter letter, chiefly family news #1289
- Fairfax Harrison to Burton N. Harrison 1900 Oct 2
  Harrison writes to his father describing the funeral of their cousin John, Lord Fairfax #1289
- J. Keim Stauffer to Francis B. Harrison 1894 Dec 24
  Refers to genealogical information on their shared Randolph ancestry #1289
- Letters to Constance Cary Harrison 1897 Mar 9, Nov 1
  from literary admirers seeking her assistance on genealogy or colonial history #1289
- Clippings of Jesse Burton Harrison's editorials in the Louisiana Advertiser1836
  from the four months preceding the 1836 presidential election, all from a staunch Whig, anti-Jacksonian view #1289
- Clippings of Reviews of Constance Cary Harrison's novel Flower de Hundred1890 Dec 15, n.d.
  #1289
- Miscellaneous Printed Materials 1881-1898, n.d.
  Articles written by Constance Cary Harrison, articles about Virginia families, and an autographed short aide-memoir by C.C. Harrison about their connection with Monticello #1289
- Francis B. Harrison to Fairfax Harrison 1910 May 14
  Refers to the letters of John Harrison to J.B. Harrison #1289-a
- John Harrison to Jesse B. Harrison 1832-1833, [1834]
  News about mutual friends' affairs and intrigues in New Orleans since J.B. Harrison's departure. Several references to duels #1289-a
- Microfilm of the Quezon (Philippines) Conversations 1935-1938
  held by Harrison with many government leaders particularly Manuel Quezon #1293
- Archibald Cary to his sisters and brother-in-law 1836-1843
  Give news of his travels and affairs. Wonderful descriptions of trips north and into the mid-west and deep South. Discuss business concerns. Also autographed bill of sale. Copies of letters to his brother Wilson Miles Cary discuss business, recovery from the Panic of 1837, political issues, family news, and the birth of his children #1308
- Autographed Diary of Jesse Burton Harrison (1805-1841) 1829 Sep-1830 Sep
  during the year he was studying and traveling in Germany and Italy. Descriptions of European events, life, and Romantic elements #1325
- Constance Cary Harrison to an editor, William H. Rideing 1897-1910, n.d.
  Discuss literary business and suggestions for articles and stories. C. C. Harrison tells of her sons' involvement in the Spanish-American War #1417